地          球          脉          动
地球的两极都被冰覆盖着
Both poles of our planet are covered with ice.
是最大、最荒凉的无人区
They're the largest and most demanding wildernesses of all.
两极地区的季节变化非常极端
Nowhere else on Earth is seasonal change so extreme.
使得冰盖面积每年都在扩大和缩小
It causes the ice to advance and retreat every year.
这里的一切生命都受其影响
And all life here is governed by that.
冰     封     世     界
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
第一批极地探险家前往南方时候
When the first polar explorers headed south,
经过这里的冰山就标志他们进入了未知领域
giant cathedrals of ice marked their entry into uncharted territory.
在经过高耸的冰山的时候
Passing the towering spires,
他们必曾感慨于地球上竟有如此别样的地方存在
they must have wondered what unearthly sights lay in store.
他们继续南上 触目皆是寒冰
As they battled on, the ice became increasingly dominant,
当冰雪世界真实的出现在他们眼前的时候 他们感到的是无法用语言形容的震撼
but nothing could have prepared them for the ice world that finally loomed into view.
这里就是未知之地 拉丁语中的“Terra Incognita”！
Terra incognita, ''the unknown land''.
南极洲位于地球的最南边
At the southernmost extreme of our planet,
面积相当于一个美国
the continent of Antarctica is as large as the United States of America.
这里的冰占全世界的90%
Ninety per cent of all the world's ice is found here.
在这个冰封的世界里大部分地方都死气沉沉
This frozen world is largely deserted
直到春天来临
until the start of spring.
阿德利企鹅
Adelie penguins
行色匆匆
in a hurry.
时钟滴嗒 时光飞逝
The clock is ticking.
还没等到夏季解冻期的来临 这些鸟儿就急急忙忙从冰封的海洋赶到南极
Instead of waiting for the summer melt, the new arrivals hasten south over the frozen sea.
它们来这里繁衍
They have come here to breed,
但是极地的夏天是非常短暂的
but polar summers are so short,
企鹅们必须赶在解冻期结束前做好就位的准备
they must be in position before the thaw starts.
当海冰的面积缩小的时候
As the sea ice retreats,
动物便能长驱直入来到南极的腹地
life can journey farther south.
南极富饶的海水吸引着千里之外的客人来觅食
Antarctic waters are so rich that visitors come from far and wide to harvest them.
颊带企鹅成群结队地来到这里的岸边繁衍生息
Vast numbers of chinstrap penguins come ashore to breed.
企鹅不会把蛋直接下在冰面上
No bird will lay their eggs directly onto ice
于是裸岩就成了最重要的繁殖地
so bare rock is a vital commodity.
爬上最好的地方就算辛苦也是值得的
The best patches are worth the climb.
数以万计的企鹅在此筑巢
The cliff tops are soon stained pink
它们的粪便使山顶看起来一片粉红
with the droppings of tens of thousands of nesting penguins.
只有在几乎完全被冰覆盖的陆地上
0nly in a land almost entirely covered in ice
裸岩才会被当作一块宝地
could bare rock be reckoned an oasis.
为了找到裸岩一些企鹅会一直深入到南极中心
Some will travel into the heart of the continent to find it.
这些“冰原岛峰”下面是深埋在深达一英里的冰层里的庞大山脉
These are nunataks, the exposed peaks of vast mountain ranges buried in ice over a mile deep.
这里静得可怕 只有到春天才会热闹起来
The eerie silence here is only broken in spring.
雪海燕来了 在这里求偶
The snow petrels have arrived and are courting.
南极雪海燕的领地在地球的最南方
Antarctic petrels now join the most southerly bird colony on Earth.
它们往内陆飞行300英里才来到这里繁衍
The birds have flown inland for over 300 miles to reach this breeding site.
一旦小鸟破蛋而出
0nce their eggs have hatched,
雪海燕将为觅食而不断往返海陆600英里
they will be forced repeatedly to make the 600-mile round trip to gather food in the ocean.
不过先得保护好来之不易的筑巢地 免得被其他鸟类占据
First, though, valuable nesting places must be defended from property thieves.
产蛋后雪海燕会在抽出时间在雪地里整理羽毛
After laying their eggs, the petrels take time out to clean their plumage.
南极贼鸥是可怕的机会主义者
The south polar skua is a formidable opportunist.
但是贼鸥碰到海燕并非机遇使然, 它们早就等着下手
But the skuas have not chanced upon the petrels, they've been waiting for them.
贼鸥不需要到海洋里捕食
These birds do not need to go to the ocean for their food.
与其他猛禽相比 贼鸥的厉害在于它能在地球的最南端生存
The skuas can survive further south than any other predator
它们知道利用海燕必定寻找裸岩筑巢的弱点
by exploiting the petrels' desperate need for bare rock.
在南极洲 即使是盛夏
Even at the height of summer,
南极洲也只有不到3％的地方没有被冰封
less than three per cent of Antarctica is free of ice,
几乎所有的裸岩都集中在同一个地方
and nearly all of that exposed rock is found in one place,
即南极半岛
the Antarctic Peninsula.
这里与南极洲的其它地方相比更靠近北边, 所以春天先来到这里
Its long arm extends further north than the rest of the continent, so spring arrives here first.
解冻后出现一些风平浪静的海湾 可以躲避南极洋无情的风浪
The thaw unlocks sheltered bays that provide refuge from the relentless battering of the Southern 0cean.
水里有动静
In the depths, something stirs.
座头鲸！
Humpback whales.
它们经过5000英里的漫长旅程终于来到了这片水域
They have travelled over 5,000 miles to reach these waters.
这些鲸现在正美美地享受着磷虾大餐
The whales are harvesting krill,
冰层一融化各种各样的虾就会聚集在这里
shrimp-like creatures that begin to swarm here as soon as the ice retreats.
潜入到虾群中后
Diving into the heart of the swarm,
座头鲸会共同配合 紧密协作
teams of whales spiral round each other in close coordination.
现在座头鲸转身 利用呼吸孔吐气 喷向猎物
Now they turn, blasting air from their blowholes, and ascend towards their prey.
螺旋型的气泡网逐渐收紧,把磷虾聚在一起
The krill becomes concentrated as the spiralling net of bubbles draws inwards.
时光短暂,座头鲸昼夜不停捕食
The team of whales work round the clock for the boom is short-lived.
短暂的夏天正逐渐消失
Summer is already fading
很快冬季又到了 这些鲸鱼将不得不前往北方
and the whales will soon be forced north as winter returns.
太阳的威力逐渐减弱
The sun's influence diminishes
海洋开始结冰
and the ocean starts to freeze.
我们这个行星上最显著的季节变化正在发生
The greatest seasonal change on our planet is underway.
冰盖的面积以非凡的速度扩大
The ice grows at an extraordinary rate,
一天扩大2.5英里
advancing two and a half miles a day.
几个星期之内,整个南极大陆的面积将扩大为原来的两倍
In a matter of weeks, the continent effectively doubles in size.
生物纷纷逃离南极洲
Life flees from Antarctica.
但偏有一种生物赶来
But one creature is just arriving.
帝企鹅每年冬天便离开它们安逸的海洋家园
Every winter, emperor penguins leave the comfort of their ocean home
开始了非凡的征途
and begin a remarkable journey.
它们要前往繁殖地,几乎在离海岸100英里的内陆
They head towards their breeding grounds, almost 100 miles inland.
帝企鹅将最终到达它们出生的故乡
Eventually, the emperor penguins reach the place where they were hatched,
一个位于冰封的洋面上、到处冰山林立的地方
an area sheltered by icebergs, trapped in the frozen ocean.
在这里 它们将繁衍下一代
Here they will raise the next generation.
但是 首先每只企鹅必须找到自己的配偶
But first, each must find a mate.
雄企鹅开始唱情歌
The males begin to serenade.
如果有雌企鹅回应, 它们就结成一对,共同摆出雕像般的姿势
And if a female replies, they pair up, posing like statues.
新的企鹅对很快就会建立深厚的感情
New couples quickly form a strong bond.
它们似乎对周围的喧嚣充耳不闻
They seem oblivious to the noisy crowd around them.
为了巩固它们的关系 雄企鹅跟雌企鹅走出行列
To cement their relationship, the male steps out with his female.
它们的交配很短暂 不浪费一分钟
The brief courtship complete, there isn't a moment to lose.
求表现的压力太大
With so much pressure to perform,
任何雄企鹅都会拼命留在上面
any male would struggle to stay on top.
几周之后
Several weeks later,
绝大多数的企鹅对都会成功繁衍出下一代
and it seems that most couplings were successful.
但体力也在产蛋的过程中消耗殆尽
But producing the egg has taken its toll.
雌企鹅再也没有孵蛋的力气
The females no longer have the energy to incubate.
任务便交给了雄企鹅
The male takes over.
此时温度还是零下20摄氏度
It's still minus 20 degrees centigrade,
所以交接过程必须迅速完成
so the transfer must be done quickly
否则蛋会冻坏
or else the egg will freeze.
没有裸岩可以在上面筑巢
With no bare rock to nest on,
雄企鹅会小心翼翼地把蛋藏在自己的体袋里
the male tucks the egg into a special pouch,
可以让蛋保持足够的温度
where he can keep it warm.
交接过程需要双方高度的配合
It requires an extraordinary piece of teamwork.
在饥饿的驱使下
Driven by hunger,
精疲力竭的雌企鹅们独自返回海洋
the exhausted females now return to the ocean on their own,
再次踏上了1月前曾和雄企鹅共同走过的漫漫征途
repeating the epic journey they made with the males only a month before.
现在太阳只能勉强升到地平线上方
Now the sun barely appears above the horizon.
随着白昼的缩短,南极大陆变得越来越冷
As the days shorten, its warmth is withdrawn from the continent.
雌企鹅去了之后
With the females gone,
企鹅的领地开始出现奇特的变化
the colony undergoes a strange transformation.
雄企鹅们聚集在一起,此时它们的蛋仍然藏在脚上面
The males shuffle into groups, their eggs still tucked away above their feet.
它们紧紧挤成包围圈以此取暖
They lock together in tightly-packed huddles as they struggle to keep warm.
在快镜头下我们可以看到包围圈在不断地变动
Speeding up the action reveals how these huddles constantly shift and change
每只企鹅都要变换位置以进入更温暖的内部
as each penguin works its way towards the warmer interior.
这些企鹅性情特别温和 这是环境使然
Crammed into this scrum, the birds are remarkably good-natured. But they have to be.
如果包围圈散了,哪怕就一小会儿 宝贵的热气也会消散
If the huddle breaks, even for a moment, precious heat escapes.
它们必须尽最大的努力重新组成队列
It's imperative they reform as quickly as possible,
因为只有团结成一体
for only by acting as one
雄企鹅才能抵挡严酷的自然力量 才能保护好它们的蛋
can the males withstand the elements and protect their eggs.
但是最大的考验还在前头
But their greatest test lies ahead.
随着隆冬的逼近,暴风雪越来越频繁 温度越来越低
As winter advances, frequent blizzards drive the temperature down.
现在已经是零下60度
It's now 60 degrees below zero.
处于边缘的企鹅承受着时速100英里的狂风袭击
The birds at the edge of the huddle bear the brunt of the 100-mile-an-hour winds
以便保护轮流站在中央的企鹅
and so provide shelter to those taking their turn in the middle.
太阳已经完全消失,雄企鹅们与它们的蛋相依为命
Abandoned by the sun, the males are left alone with their eggs
来抵抗这地球上最寒冷、最黑暗的冬天
to face the coldest, darkest winter on Earth.
而在地球的北极
At the northern extreme of our planet,
太阳在数个月的沉寂后第一次升起
the sun rises for the first time in months,
阳光照亮了一个截然不同的冰的世界
illuminating a very different ice world.
与南极不同
Unlike Antarctica,
北极是广阔的冰封海洋 被陆地包围
the Arctic is a vast frozen sea surrounded by land.
这里的冬天已经临近尾声
Here winter is coming to an end
但这片荒凉的无人区仍然是冰封的天地
but this bleak wilderness remains locked in ice.
绒鸭的到来打破了这里的平静
Eider ducks break the silence.
绒鸭没有迁徙到温暖的南方
They have stayed here, braving the northern winter,
而一直坚守在这里经受着北方寒冬的考验
instead of flying south to warmer climes.
4万只绒鸭飞越这一片冰天雪地的荒野
Flocks 40,000 strong sweep across the frozen wastes.
它们都有相同的目标--冰间湖（冰穴）
They all have the same goal, a polynya,
冰间湖是结冰的海洋上永久性的洞孔 因为有强大的洋流使它们冬天也不会冰封
a permanent hole in the sea ice, kept open throughout the winter by strong ocean currents.
这个不同寻常的水池是过夜的庇护所
This unusual duck pond provides an overnight sanctuary
而且到了白天还有难得的进食机会
and, when day breaks, a rare chance to feed.
就在离冰面10米以下的海底上
Just 10 metres beneath the ice,
布满了密密麻麻的贻贝
the sea floor is carpeted with dense mussel beds.
这个地方只有在洋流暂时停歇时才能吃到
These can only be reached during a brief lull in the currents.
绒鸭必须赶在潮流转向之前迅速采食
The ducks must quickly prise the mussels free before the tide starts to turn.
机会之窗随时可能关闭
The window of opportunity is short.
洋流开始转强时它们就只好远走高飞了
As the current begins to build, it's up, up and away.
这个长年不冻的水窟窿提供了整整一个冬天的食物
These permanent holes in the ice provide seafood throughout the winter.
其它生物也似乎闻风而来
The diners attract others.
在北极 每一处破冰的地方都是一条生命线
In the Arctic, any breach in the icy barrier can be a lifeline.
麝牛创造了自己的生命线
Musk oxen create their own.
这种体型巨大的动物有足够的力量砸出冰窟窿
These giants have the strength to smash through the frozen crust
再吃下面的植物
to graze on the vegetation below.
麝牛破冰也为其它越冬的动物创造机会
The ice-breakers create an opening for other over-winterers.
成群的雷鸟与麝牛结成了紧密的伙伴关系
Flocks of ptarmigan make unusual grazing companions for the musk oxen,
它们的活动忙碌一整天
whose entourage grows throughout the day.
这些食草动物组成的奇特群落当然会引起注意
This odd assembly of vegetarians doesn't go unnoticed.
一头北极狐
An arctic fox.
麝牛最近生了幼仔
The musk oxen have recently given birth.
对于北极狐来说 这是一个捕食的机会
For the fox, it's a chance to scavenge.
不过在半数是脾气暴躁的母牛面前不好硬来
But half a ton of mad hairy cow is not to be trifled with.
牛犊出生在春天冰盖融化之前
The calves are born well before the spring melt,
这样可以顺利地迎接夏天的到来
giving them a head start when summer finally arrives.
它们必须适应这个冰雪世界
It must get to grips with its new ice world,
但天气喜怒无常
benign one minute, life-threatening the next.
即使是春天 仍然寒风彻骨
Even in spring, winds chill to the bone.
小牛必须紧跟着母亲 才能避免在突如其来的暴风雪中迷路
The calf must stay close to its mother to avoid getting lost in the sudden blizzard.
北极狼
Arctic wolves!
在白茫茫的天气中 有危险也几乎不可能察觉到
In the whiteout, the threat is almost impossible to detect,
但是麝牛本能地向高地撤退
but the musk oxen instinctively retreat to higher ground.
成牛围成圈以保护它们的小牛, 一般的猎食动物很难突破这层封锁
Forming a defensive ring around their calves, the adults present a barricade that few hunters could breach.
但是今天的这头狼不需要冒受伤的危险硬闯
But the wolves need not risk injury today.
它们在慌乱之中留下一头小牛
A calf has been left behind in the panic.
随着时间一天天过去,天上的太阳升得越来越高
With each passing day, the sun climbs higher in the sky
阳光逐渐直射到北极来
and its rays strike the Arctic more directly.
新的生命在春天的气息中开始蠢蠢欲动
It's spring and new life stirs.
小北极熊从洞穴中探出头来
The polar bear cubs emerge from the den in which they were born.
它们的母亲在雪下呆了5个月后终于可以出来伸伸腿
Their mother stretches her legs after five months under the snow.
小熊才两个月大
They are just two months old
本能地跟在母亲后面
and instinctively follow her lead.
陡峭的斜坡是穴居的好地点
A steep slope makes the best site for a den,
但第一次踏出脚时是不能掉以轻心的
but it's a tricky place to take your first steps.
可能看起来很好玩, 但这都是为马上来临的严峻挑战所做的训练
It may look like fun but this is serious training for the task ahead.
山坡上面没有食物
There is no food on the slopes
在母熊奶水干涸之前 一家人需要穿越冰封的海洋
and the family will need to head out across the frozen sea before the mother's milk runs dry.
两周后它们做好了准备
Two weeks later, they are ready.
雌熊有可能在海冰上捕食到海豹
0ut on the sea ice, the female can hunt for seals
但是这个冰雪世界危机四伏
but it will take all her mothering skills to keep her cubs safe
要保护好自己的幼仔 母熊必须施展出所有的本领
in this dangerous world of ice.
每年一次的解冻期来了
The annual melt has begun.
对于北极熊一家来说 这是一个极富挑战性的时刻
This is a challenging time for the bear family.
两只幼熊中往往会有一只无法在第一年存活下来
0ne out of every two cubs do not survive their first year out on the ice.
随着太阳的威力逐渐增强, 海冰仿佛有了自己的生命
As the sun's influence increases, the sea ice seems to take on a life of its own.
融化了的冰川水从陆地上喷泻而出
Glacial melt waters pour from the land, mingling with the sea
与海水交汇 加速了解冻
and speeding up the thaw.
海洋在不断地变迁, 破裂的冰块在风和洋流的作用下不停地移动着
The seascape is in constant flux as broken ice is moved on by winds and currents.
冰面开始变薄 已经很难承受一只雄性北极熊的重量
The ice is becoming too weak to support a male polar bear.
这只北极熊试图分散身体的重量
He attempts to spread his weight,
但是在冬天能够支撑它的冰面现在正迅速地解体
but the ice that has supported him all winter is rapidly disintegrating.
每年的天气变暖时 北冰洋的冰就会减少
Each year, as the climate warms, the Arctic holds less ice.
对于北极熊而言 这是一场灾难
This is a disaster for polar bears.
没有坚实的冰作为平台, 北极熊就不能猎捕它们赖以生存的海豹
Without its solid platform, they can't hunt the seals they need in order to survive.
这种巨大生物的前途很不乐观
This may be a glimpse of the unstable future faced by this magnificent creature.
冰融化的时候 海鸟返回到北冰洋
As the ice disappears, seabirds return to the high Arctic.
小海雀成千上万地飞来
Little auks arrive in their millions.
在一些人的眼里, 这些海雀是北极的企鹅
In some ways, these birds are the penguins of the north.
它们寻找裸岩 好在上面产蛋, 它们长得也有几分像企鹅
They seek bare rock on which to lay their eggs and they look rather like penguins, too.
与南极不同, 陆基的掠食动物也可以到达这里
Unlike Antarctica, the Arctic can be reached by land-based predators,
所以小海雀仍然需要保持飞行能力
which is why little auks have kept the ability to fly.
它们利用岩肖山坡保护鸟蛋
They use scree slopes to protect their eggs,
蛋藏在岩石下的深达1米的缝隙里
burrowing up to a metre beneath the rocks.
盛夏的太阳从不落山
At the height of summer, the sun never sets,
只是滑落在地平线上 再次升起
but just skims the horizon before rising again.
候鸟们从世界各地返回北极
Migrants return to the Arctic from far and wide.
它们来寻找美食和繁衍后代
They've come to make the most of the brief flush of food and to produce their young.
沙丘鹤则从新墨西哥州一路赶到这里
Sandhill cranes have travelled all the way from New Mexico.
它们的小鸟跟其他小鸟一起探索冻土地带
Their chicks join the growing band of youngsters exploring the tundra.
每年有几个月的时间
For a few months each year,
北极变成了所谓的“午夜太阳之地”
the Arctic becomes ''The land of the midnight sun''
一天24小时都是白昼 动物可以24小时觅食
and 24 hours of daylight allow animals to feed around the clock.
北极狐终于有足够的食物来养活它的大家庭
The arctic fox finally has enough food to raise her large family.
选择了空旷地筑巢也就必须做好厮杀角逐的准备
If you choose to nest in the open, you must be prepared for a fight.
北极贼鸥会袭击任何侵犯它的领地的动物 甚至大型的草食动物
Arctic skuas will see off any trespassers, even large vegetarians.
冰雪世界最后在雄北极熊的脚下消失了
The male polar bear's ice world has finally vanished beneath him.
雌熊仍然在陆地上照顾小熊
While the female is still kept on land by her dependent cubs,
公熊则来到大海里寻找食物
the male can take to the sea in search of food. Ducking and diving,
潜伏在水中准备袭击在残留的冰块上休息的海豹
he hopes to ambush seals resting on the remaining fragments of ice.
在这个新环境里, 北极熊变成了一个身怀绝技的游泳高手
In these new surroundings, he is a surprisingly adept swimmer.
曾经有人在离海岸60英里处发现了北极熊 这种事情是极难碰到的
0nce an extremely rare sight, polar bears have recently been seen over 60 miles from the shore.
现在已经没有回头路了
There is now no turning back for this bear.
它必须进入更深的水域
He is forced to head out into deeper water.
它那巨大的前爪有力地拨动着海水
His giant front paws help him to fight the ocean currents.
在海里它似乎是那样地悠游自在
He seems at home in the sea,
但是它不能永远游在水里
but he cannot swim indefinitely.
如果在这片汪洋里一直找不到陆地它就会淹死
He will drown if he doesn't find land somewhere in this vast ocean.
海象正往低岛聚集
Walruses are now gathering on low-lying islands.
它们在海冰上产仔
They gave birth on the sea ice,
但这块平台已经消失,它们需要新的地方哺育幼仔
but with this platform now gone, they need a new place to haul out and nurse their young.
在海上漂流了几天之后公熊终于登陆了
After several days at sea, the male bear finally makes landfall,
它已经嗅到了岛屿上散发出的强烈气味
drawn by the pungent smells emanating from the island.
但在夏天结束时,公熊的体重已经减少了一半
By the end of the summer, the bear has lost half his weight.
冰层早已融化,迫使它到陆地上寻找食物
With the ice long gone, he is forced onto land in search of food.
在这座岛上找到吃的并不容易
There will be no easy meals on this island.
海象是世界上最大的海豹科动物.
Walruses are the largest seals in the world.
体重超过1吨,有长达1米的象牙为武器
They weigh over a ton and are armed with tusks a metre long.
游得精疲力竭的北极熊必须恢复体力
Exhausted from his swim, the bear must regain his strength.
第二天海雾笼罩了这座岛屿
The next day, a sea fog shrouds the island.
海象已经意识到危险
The walruses sense that they are in danger.
在海雾的掩护下,北极熊向海象群靠近
Using the fog as cover, the bear approaches the herd.
但成象围成圈保护小象, 构成了一堵坚固的脂肪皮墙
The adults close ranks around their young, presenting a wall of blubber and hide.
它先试探了一下但那里很坚固
He tests the barrier, but it stands firm.
看起来这个世界上最大的陆地食肉动物遇到了对手
It appears that the world's largest land carnivore has met his match.
一定在什么地方有破绽
There must be a chink in the armour somewhere.
不在这里
Not here!
雌海象在保护它的小象 如果能够把它拉开的话…
This female walrus is shielding her pup, if he can just prise her off...
但熊的尖牙利爪都无法穿透海象厚实的毛皮
The bear's claws and teeth can't penetrate her thick hide.
象群开始往水里撤退,熊必须迅速出击
With the herd retreating to water, the bear must move quickly.
一个失败后 它又径直奔向另一个
Having failed with one, he heads straight for another.
挨饿几个月后吃到第一顿饭的希望正变得越来越渺茫
The chance of his first meal in months is slipping away.
看起来它变得越来越拼命
He seems increasingly desperate.
这是生死关头
It's now or never.
它必须躲开戳过来的象牙才能取胜
He must avoid the stabbing tusks if he is to win.
但不断甩动身体的海象力气大得惊人, 它从浅滩被拖到海象群所在的安全地点
The flailing walrus is immensely powerful and drags the bear away from the shallows towards the safety of the herd.
海象从北极熊的爪子下面逃走了
It slips from his grasp.
只有在盛夏 到了饿死的边缘
0nly at the height of summer,
才会攻击这样危险的对象
when bears are on the verge of starvation, will they risk attacking such dangerous prey.
这只熊赌命一搏却输了
It was a gamble that this bear took and lost.
它受了重伤 现在连走路都很困难
The stab wounds he received from the walrus are so severe that he can barely walk.
海象们恢复了平静
The walruses are calm again,
似乎意识到受伤的熊 再也不会对自己和幼仔构成威胁
seemingly aware that the injured bear no longer poses a threat to them or their young.
找不到食物,这只熊将无法活下来
Unable to feed, this bear will not survive.
如果全球气候继续变暖
If the global climate continues to warm,
北极冰层融化的时间继续提前
and the Arctic ice melts sooner each year,
肯定会有越来越多的熊遭受这样的命运
it is certain that more bears will share this fate.
在我们行星的最南方
At the southern end of our planet,
火焰一样的极光照亮了冬季的夜空
fiery ribbons are illuminating the winter skies.
南极光
The aurora australis.
这道光并没有给还挤成一堆的雄企鹅带来温暖,
This light brings no warmth to the male penguins,
它们还挤在一起面对着地球上最严酷的挑战
who are still huddling, defying the coldest conditions on the planet.
但磨难已经接近尾声
Their ordeal is drawing to a close.
南极洲的太阳在落山30天后 再次升起
Thirty days after it last set, the sun rises once more on Antarctica.
它们所经受的可怕考验就是为了这一刻
Their appalling trials have all been for this.
每个企鹅爸爸的嘴里都含着一口食物
Each father has just one meal left inside him.
这口食物已经储存了整整一个冬天
He has been saving it all winter.
就这一口吃的可以让小企鹅多存活几天
This single feed will sustain the chicks for a few more days,
但是雄企鹅已经四个月没有进食
but the males have not eaten for nearly four months.
如果再不快点吃东西 它们和小企鹅都会死掉
If they do not eat soon, they and their chicks will die.
但是希望就在地平线那边
But there is hope on the horizon.
雌企鹅们回来了,吃了一肚子的鱼回来了
The females are returning and their bellies are full with fish.
随着它们脚步的临近, 雄企鹅们开始表现出抑制不住的兴奋
As they approach, waves of excitement ripple through the huddle.
雌企鹅们各自呼唤配偶
Each female calls to her mate and he,
雄企鹅听到后就会大声回应
recognising her song, trumpets back.
终于大团圆了！
Reunited at last.
企鹅妈妈第一次看到企鹅宝宝
The mother sees her chick for the first time.
便急不可待地想马上尽妈妈的责任
She's keen to start parenting,
但整个冬天都在照顾小企鹅的爸爸倒是有点舍不得
but the father needs persuading to surrender the chick he has been caring for all winter.
它现在要让小企鹅冒险, 在这种温度下 小企鹅随时有可能冻死
He must now put his chick at risk. In these temperatures it could freeze in seconds.
雄企鹅还是得放手
The male will have to let go.
宝宝终于安全地交给了妈妈
Eventually, the transfer to the mother is safely made.
小企鹅长得很快,吃小鱼和鱿鱼
The chicks grow quickly on a diet of fish and squid.
很快它们可以自由行动了
Soon they are keen to explore,
不过妈妈总在旁边照看着
but always with mother in tow.
这是一只不幸的小企鹅
This chick is less fortunate,
它的妈妈没有来认养它
its mother has not returned to claim it.
另一只没妈妈的小企鹅在寻找新家庭
Another orphan is searching for a new family,
但这只雌企鹅已经有了自己的宝宝
but this female already has a chick of her own.
有些失去亲鸟的小企鹅受到了母鸟们过分的关注
Some orphans receive too much mothering from penguins whose own chicks have not survived.
这些母鸟们自己的宝宝夭折了 便争养任何碰到的孤儿
The urge to parent is so strong that they will compete with one another to adopt any chick they find.
这样的争来争去往往会以悲剧收尾
Many of these squabbles end in tragedy
可怜的小企鹅有可能被活活压死
as the poor chick is trampled to death.
而有父母的小企鹅很快就要学习生存的技能
Those chicks that do have parents quickly learn survival skills.
即使在春天 小企鹅们也必须挤在一起
Even in spring, they must huddle together for warmth,
就像寒冬时节它们的爸爸做的那样
just as their fathers did in the depths of winter.
有一群小企鹅在暴风雪中迷路了
A group of chicks has got lost in the blizzard.
迷失方向的它们在寒冷中四处寻找亲人
Cold and disorientated, they search for the colony.
很快暴风雪中就会出现几具尸体
It will not be long before the storm claims its first victims.
到了初夏 小企鹅已经发育得非常良好
By early summer, the chicks are surprisingly well-developed
它们已经做好了当上这个世界的主人的准备
and now look ready to take on the world.
那些在第一年里 存活下来的小企鹅有着最光明的前途
Those that survive their first year have the best possible start in life
多亏了它们的爸爸和妈妈承受了非凡的考验
thanks to the extraordinary hardships endured by their parents.
在同南极的冬天抗争并取得了胜利
Parents who battled with the Antarctic winter and won.
在北冰洋  两只小北极熊现在可以离开妈妈独立生活了
In the Arctic, the two polar bear cubs are now independent of their mother
之前它们曾短暂地在陆地的家园团聚过
and they briefly reunite where their home ranges overlap.
它们在一起的时间很短
Their time together will be fleeting.
它们一生的大部分时间都独来独往
Most of their lives are now spent alone,
在冰封的海洋上四处游猎
wandering the vast tracts of frozen ocean.
在跟它们母亲在一起的时候
Following their mother
它们已经学会怎样生存在极地
has prepared them for life at the pole,
在这个永远在变的冰的国度
an ever-changing land ruled by ice.
它们是否已经做好了适应更大的变化
Whether they are ready for the bigger changes
适应已经开始影响这个冰雪世界的变化的准备, 还不得而知.
that have begun to shape the ice worlds of our planet remains to be seen.